Preliminary Inventory of the Military Order of the World Wars records
Hoover Institution Archives
Military Order of the World Wars records
1876-2010
65029
Hoover Institution Archives
341 manuscript boxes, 15 oversize boxes, 6 card file boxes, 1 oversize folder (150 linear feet)
Biographical data on members, chapter histories, minutes, convention proceedings, memoirs, printed matter, photographs, memorabilia, relating to American military activities, especially in World War I, World War II, the Korean War, and the Vietnamese War; and to veterans' activities.
Military Order of the World Wars
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/ to find the full extent of the collection.
Historical Note
Patriotic American organization of former military officers.
Scope and Content Note
Biographical data on members, chapter histories, minutes, convention proceedings, memoirs, printed matter, photographs, memorabilia, relating to American military activities, especially in World War I, World War II, the Korean War, and the Vietnamese War; and to veterans' activities.
United States. Air Force.; United States. Army.; United States. Marine Corps.; United States. Navy.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--History, Military.; Veterans--United States.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Biographies (Box 1)
  - General - Biographical sketches, clippings, memoirs
    - General
      - A-M
      - N-Z (Box 2)
    - Allin, Benjamin Casey, III, Colonel (Box 3)
    - Bushey, Arthur Clifton, Jr., Commander (Box 4)
    - Dodge, Morton Moore, Colonel
    - Geiger, Vincent A.
    - Navarre, Christopher P., Chief Warrant Officer (Box 5)
    - Port, Horace, Brigadier General
    - Ramsey, Edwin Price, Lieutenant Colonel
    - Sinks, George T., Major
  - Who's Who forms (arranged by chapter name and therein alphabetically by Companion name). (Box 6)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes some chapter bulletins, histories, and rosters
    - Unspecified
    - Anchorage
    - Andrews AFB
    - Apache Trail
    - Atlanta
    - Augusta (Box 7)
    - Austin
    - Baltimore-Devereux Memorial
    - Baton Rouge, LA-Gen. Troy H. Middleton
    - Berkeley (defunct) (Box 8)
    - Bethesda
    - Boise Valley (defunct)
    - Bradenton/Sarasota (Box 9)
    - Burlington (defunct)
    - Cajon Valley-San Diego (merged with General J. Paul Holland) (Box 10)
    - Canal Zone (defunct)
    - Cape Cod
    - Cdr Simpson-Ltc Loring
    - Central Alabama (defunct) (Box 11)
    - Central Arkansas
    - Central Florida
    - Central New Jersey (defunct)
    - Central Pennsylvania
    - Central Texas Area (merged with Hill Country Texas)
    - Charlotte
    - Chicago (Box 12-13)
    - Cincinnati
    - Clearwater
    - Cleveland
    - Col John M. Birkner (Box 15)
    - Col Pendleton Woods/Oklahoma City
    - Colorado Springs
    - Columbia
    - Columbus, GA
    - Conejo Valley
    - Coral Gables (merged with Miami)
    - Corpus Christi
    - Dallas (Box 16-18)
    - Daytona Beach (Box 19)
    - Denver (Box 20)
    - Detroit
    - East Texas (Box 21)
    - El Paso
    - Emerald Empire (defunct)
    - Fairfield Bay (defunct)
    - Flagler-Palm Coast (defunct)
    - Florida Gold Coast (defunct)
    - Fort Benning (defunct) (Box 22)
    - Fort Buchanan (changed name to Puerto Rico)
    - Fort Hood
    - Fort Huachuca
    - Fort Snelling
    - Fort Walton Beach
    - Fort Worth
    - Frankfort
    - Fresno (merged with Monterey Bay)
    - G/A Omar N. Bradley (Box 23)
    - General Critz
    - General George G. Meade
    - General Hoyt S. Vandenberg
    - General J. Paul Holland
    - General Joshua Chamberlain
    - General Leigh Wade-D.C. (Box 24)
    - General M. B. Ridgway-Pittsburgh
    - General Westmoreland/Charleston
    - Granite State
    - Great Salt Lake
    - Greater Boston (Box 25)
    - Greater Kansas City
    - Green Mountain
    - Gulf Coast (changed name to Capt Maltby-Pensacola, then merged with Fort Walton Beach) (Box 26)
    - Gunpowder (defunct)
    - Hampton Roads
    - Hann-Buswell Memorial
    - Hartford (defunct)
    - Harvey Latham
    - Headquarters (Box 27)
    - Hill Country Texas
    - Honolulu (changed name to Gaylord Dillingham Memorial) (Box 28)
    - Houston (Box 29)
    - Huntsville
    - Illowa
    - Indiana
    - Indianapolis
    - Jackson
    - Jacksonville
    - Joseph H. Pendleton
    - Key West (defunct) (Box 30)
    - Knoxville
    - Lafayette (defunct) (Box 31)
    - Laguna Hills (defunct)
    - Las Vegas
    - Leisure World
    - Long Beach (merged with G/A Omar N. Bradley) (Box 32)
    - Los Angeles (defunct) (Box 33)
    - Louisville
    - Lt Richard F. Williams Memorial (merged with Santa Fe)
    - Ltg John M. Wright, Jr.
    - Major Cyrill H. Pfohl (defunct) (Box 34)
    - Memphis
    - Mendenhall Memorial (defunct)
    - Mesilla Valley
    - Mg Franklin E. Miles
    - Miami (Box 35)
    - Mid-Michigan
    - Middle Georgia
    - Middle Tennessee (defunct)
    - Milwaukee
    - Mississippi Coast
    - Monroe (Box 36)
    - Monterey Bay
    - Narragansett Bay
    - New Bedford (merged with Narragansett Bay)
    - New Haven
    - New London (Box 37)
    - New Orleans
    - New York (defunct) (Box 38-43)
    - Norfolk (defunct)
    - North Suncoast (defunct)
    - Northern New Jersey
    - Northern Virginia
    - Oakland (defunct) (Box 45)
    - Orange County (defunct)
    - Oro Valley (changed name to Catalina Mountains)
    - Palo Alto-Stanford (merged with San Francisco) (Box 46)
    - Paris, France (defunct)
    - Pasadena (Box 47)
    - Pecos Valley
    - Peninsula (defunct) (Box 48)
    - Philadelphia (Box 48-50)
    - Phoenix (Box 51)
    - Piney Woods (defunct)
    - Pinson Memorial
    - Ponce, Puerto Rico (changed name to Puerto Rico) (Box 52)
    - Portland
    - Prince George's County (Box 53)
    - Puerto Rico
    - Quad-Cities (changed name to Illowa)
    - Reno-Carson City (defunct)
    - Richmond
    - Roanoke
    - Sacramento (defunct)
    - Saddleback Valley
    - San Antonio (Box 54)
    - San Clemente
    - San Diego (Box 55-57)
    - San Fernando Valley (Box 58)
    - San Francisco
    - San Juan, Puerto Rico (changed name to Puerto Rico)
    - Santa Barbara
    - Santa Cruz Valley (Box 59)
    - Santa Fe
    - Savannah
    - Seattle (defunct) (Box 60)
    - South Bay (defunct) (Box 61)
    - Southern Maryland
    - Southwest Florida
    - Space Coast-Indian River
    - Spokane (merged with The Puget Sound)
    - Springfield, MA (defunct)
    - Springfield, MO (defunct)
    - St Augustine
    - St Louis
    - St Paul (defunct)
    - St Petersburg (merged with Clearwater)
    - Sun Cities
    - Sun City Center
    - Tallahassee (Box 63)
    - Tampa (defunct)
    - The Puget Sound
    - Topeka
    - Tucson (mreged with Catalina Mountains)
    - Vadm George C. Dyer-Annapolis (Box 64-66)
    - Ventura County (Box 67)
    - Victoria Crossroads (Cadre)
    - Virginia Beach
    - Virginia Piedmont
    - Western North Carolina (Cadre) (defunct)
    - Whidbey Island (defunct)
    - White Sands (defunct)
    - Wichita
    - Wilmington, DE
    - Wilmington, NC (changed name to Col Bill Sheets)
    - Worcester
- Bulletins (Box 68)
  - Departments
    - Arizona
    - California
    - California (Box 69)
    - Florida (Box 70)
    - Maryland
    - Oklahoma
    - Texas
    - Washington
  - Headquarters
  - Regions (Box 71)
    - I-VI
    - VII-XV (Box 72)
- Circulars of Historian General, 1957-1958 (Box 73)
- Committee file
  - Education, 1983-1985
  - History and Archives
- Correspondence, 1932-1967
- Founding documents.
  Includes material of the first national convention in Detroit, Michigan, in 1920
- Histories (Box 74)
  - General
    - "A History of the Founding and First Years of the Military Order of the World Wars."
      Typescript
    - "History of the Military Order of the World Wars: .", 1919-1945
    - "History of the Military Order of the World Wars: .", 1946-1969
  - The History of the Military Order of the World Wars: Its First Fifty Years, by George C. Dyer. (Box 75)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - The Military Order of the World Wars, A Living History: Decade of the 1970s, by Karl B. Justus.
  - The Military Order of the World Wars, A Living History: Decade of the 1980s, by Karl B. Justus.
    Printed copy
  - Chapters (by original name of chapter). (Box 76)
    Includes some bulletins
    - General.
      Includes instructions for chapter histories
    - Annapolis
    - Atlanta - Bradenton (Box 77)
    - Bradenton - Central Florida (Box 78)
    - Central New Jersey - Columbia (Box 79)
    - Dallas (Box 80)
    - Daytona - Easton (Box 81)
    - El Paso (Box 82)
    - Fort Walton Beach - Gunpowder (Box 83)
    - Hann-Buswell Memorial - Inland Empire (Box 84)
    - Jacksonville (Box 85)
    - La Jolla (Box 86-98)
    - Lee County - Long Beach (Box 99)
    - Long Beach (Box 100)
    - Long Beach - Louisville (Box 101)
    - Maine - Memphis (Box 102)
    - Miami - New Bedford (Box 103)
    - New Haven - Norfolk (Box 104)
    - North Virginia - Palo Alto (Box 105)
    - Peninsula (Box 106)
    - Peninsula - Philadelphia (Box 107)
    - Philadelphia (Box 108)
    - Phoenix (Box 109)
    - Pittsburgh (Box 110-112)
    - Portland - Roanoke (Box 113)
    - Sacramento - San Antonio
    - San Antonio (Box 115-116)
    - San Antonio - Santa Cruz Valley (Box 117)
    - Sarasota - Seattle (Box 118)
    - Seattle - Southwest Florida (Box 119)
    - St Louis - Worcester (Box 120)
  - Departments (Box 121-124)
    - California.
      General note
      See also Oversize material/Scrapbooks
    - Florida (Box 124-125)
    - Georgia (Box 125)
  - Regions (Box 125-127)
- List of life members, 1950 (Box 128)
- Memoranda
  - Headquarters, 1988-1989
  - Resolutions Committee, 1989
- Minutes of meetings
  - Departments
  - Executive Committee and General Staff (Box 129)
    - 1959-1966
    - 1970-1978 (Box 130)
    - 1979-1984 (Box 131)
    - Miscellaneous
- Personal files of Colonel Benjamin C. Allin, III (Box 132-135)
- Proceedings of national and regional conventions. (Box 136)
  See also Histories/Chapters
  - 1920-1946
  - 1947-1954 (Box 137)
  - 1955-1959 (Box 138)
  - 1960-1963 (Box 139)
  - 1965-1967 (Box 140)
  - 1967-1969 (Box 141)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 142)
  - 1971-1974 (Box 143)
  - 1975-1979 (Box 144)
  - 1980-1983 (Box 145)
  - 1983-1985
  - 1985-1987 (Box 147)
  - 1987-1990 (Box 148)
  - Miscellaneous
- Publications (many missing issues) (Box 149)
  - Armed Forces Day Review, 1950-1989
  - National Bulletin, 1934-1962 (Box 150)
  - Officer Review, and, 1974-1999 2002-2010 (Box 150-152)
- Reference requests (Box 153)
- Reports of Historian General, 1967-1969
- Rosters
  - Chapter officers, 1990
  - National officers, 1961-1965
- Subject file
  - Brown Cup
  - Forrestal, James V.
  - High School Prep
  - MacArthur, Douglas A., General
  - Medal of Honor recipients in MOWW
  - Military training camps - United States
  - ROTC
  - United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces
  - World War, - Maps, 1914-1918 (Map case)
  - Youth Leadership Conference (Box 153)
- Writings. Mostly reminiscences of Companions (Box 154)
  - A-C
  - D (Box 155)
  - D-H (Box 156)
  - K-P (Box 157)
  - P-W (Box 158)
- Oversize material (Box 159)
  - Certificates, diplomas, etc.
  - Photocopy of United Nations declaration, 1942 January 1
  - Printed matter - Fifty Years of Military Life:, 1940-1990
  - Scrapbooks - Department of California histories (Box 160)
    - 1954-1958
    - 1958-1959 (Box 161)
    - 1960-1962 (Box 162)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 163)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 164)
- Memorabilia - Framed letter by Herbert Hoover commending the M.O.W.W. on Army Day, April 5, 1930
- Photographs (Box 165)
  - Album of photographs depicting General George Armstrong Custer and his family, other officers and their wives, and Sioux chief Sitting Bull, as well as material relating to Major James M. Burns' career and personal life, and to his account of the battle of Little Big Horn, 1876-1896
  - Photograph of Brigadier General Douglas MacArthur in France during World War I (Box 166)
  - Album of photographs of military operations in the Philippines and New Guinea,, including some depicting General Douglas MacArthur, 1944
  - Miscellaneous photographs
- Miscellany material (Box 167-169)
- Alphabetical files (Box 169)
  - A
  - A-C (Box 170)
  - C-E (Box 171)
  - E-F (Box 172)
  - G (Box 173-176)
  - H (Box 176)
  - I-M (Box 177)
  - M-P (Box 178)
  - P-R (Box 179)
  - S-Z (Box 180)
- Card file (Box 181)
- Alphabetical files (Box 182)
  - B-C
  - C (Box 183-186)
  - D-E (Box 187)
  - E-M (Box 188)
  - N (Box 189-193)
  - O (Box 194)
  - P (Box 195)
  - R (Box 196-198)
- Miscellany (Box 198)
- Histories of chapters (Box 199-202)
  - Cajon Valley (defunct).
    See also Scrapbooks, Box 212
  - General J. Paul Holland (Box 203-209)
  - Joseph H. Pendleton (Box 209-211)
  - San Diego (Box 211)
- Scrapbooks (oversize) (Box 212)
  - Cajon Valley chapter
  - Rancho Bernardo Military Balls, San Diego (Box 213)
- Miscellany (Box 214-220)
- Personal files of Lieutenant Colonel Peter Burrows, 1965-1981 (Box 221-227)
- Personal files of Major Silas W. Bass,., 1995-2002 (Box 228)
  Includes material on the Key West chapter
- Histories of chapters
  - Annapolis. (Box 229-230)
    Includes prints, slides, film strips, phonotape cassettes, and material regarding MOWW's National Bicentennial Ad Hoc Committee for the "American Freedom Train"
  - Key West (Box 231)
  - San Diego. (Box 232)
    Catalog of items transferred to San Diego State University
- Audio-visual material
- National files of MOWW's headquarters,., 1962-2000 (Box 233-234)
  Includes Department of Washington files
- Publications - Officer Review, 2000-2010 (Box 235-236)
- Histories - General (Box 236)
  - Annual Review, by Silas W. Bass, Jr., and William A. West, vol. 1,., 1999-2000
  - Annual Review, by William A. West, vol. 2,., 2000-2001
  - Annual Review, by William A. West, vol. 3,., 2001-2002
- Photographs (Box 237)
- Empty - see box 237 (Box 238-240)
- Unsorted (Box 241-243)
- Empty - see box 237 (Box 244-245)
- Unsorted (Box 246-250)
- Oversize materials (Box 251)
- Empty - see box 251 (Box 252)
- Membership application forms (Box 253-273)
- Incremental Materials (Box 274-356)
- Tuscon chapter scrapbook, 1990-1991 (Box 357)
- Political proclamations from Maryland state locations, 2001-2009 (Box 357)
- George W. Bush letters of congratulations, 2002-2008 (Box 357)
- MOWW staff with SINC Captain Russell Volwinkel (Box 357)
- "The History of the Military Order of the World Wars," metal printing plates, galley proofs, and printed paper copies, undated (Box 357)
- Photograph and quote from Major Ennals Guaggonner CINC, 1942 (Box 357)
- Maps (Map case)
- Incremental Materials (Box 358)